Functions serve two purposes in Python. They
return a value, or they do not. In Python,
functions can return a value, perform some action,
or both. The value returned by a function can be
stored in a variable for future use or for
further calculations. In this topic, we will
see when the return keyword should be used and
when it is not needed. In this 423-return file,
I have two functions: one that calculates a total
score and another that displays a welcome message
whenever the function is called. Without going
through the code yet, which of these two functions
I just described would warrant a value stored for
later use? If you said the total score function,
you would be correct. Functions that print
messages do not need to return any values.
Those messages can be stored in a variable.
Functions that do not return any values are
often called void functions or procedures. The
welcome function on lines 4 and 5 is an example
of a function that outputs text. The reason for
the function is so that we can call the function,
as we do on line 10, as many times as we want, and
if someone wants to change the welcome message,
they need only do it once. Let’s go back to the
function on lines 1 and 2. This function has a
return statement to return the score times
the multiplier. Why the need for a return
statement and not just a print statement?
If we print the result here, we cannot use
it again in code. Look at the code on lines 7
and 8. The total score function is run twice,
and the results are stored in two variables:
score1 and score2. Then, both scores are revealed
in an f-string statement on line 11. For lines
7, 8, and 11 to work, the function on line 1 must
return a value. I will run this code, and we will
get the welcome message and the print statement
with the two scores. The return statement is
very important to understand because it allows
a function result to be used later in code as
part of a print statement or further calculation.